A Guide to the Kilby family Papers, 1665-1947
Library of Virginia
- Series II: John R. Kilby Papers, 1834-1904
  - Subseries 2: Accounts books and ledgers, 1840-1904
    - Account book as administrator of the estate and guardians of the orphans of Mills C. Daughtrey, 1858-1873 (Volume on shelf)
    - Account book of John R. Kilby, 1854-1874 (Volume on shelf)
    - Account book of sales as trustee for the estate of Archibald Riddick, 1852-1853 (Volume on shelf)
    - Account book of personal expenses of John R. Kilby, 1855-1869 (Volume on shelf)
    - Cash receipts for law practice of John R. Kilby, 1849-1869 (Volume on shelf)
    - Commissioner in Fiduciaries, Nansemond County, Va., Account book, 1849-1871 (Volume on shelf)
    - Commissioner in Fiduciaries, Nansemond County, Va., Account book, 1869-1882 (Volume on shelf)
    - Fee book, Deputy Sheriff, Nansemond County, Va., 1840-1842 (Volume on shelf)
    - Fee book, Deputy Sheriff, Nansemond County, Va., 1842-1844 (Volume on shelf)
    - Ledger, 1846-1854 (Volume on shelf)
    - Ledger, 1852-1861 (Volume on shelf)
    - Ledger, 1858-1873 (Volume on shelf)
    - Ledger, 1868-1884 (Volume on shelf)
    - Ledger, 1872-1904 (Volume on shelf)
- Series III: Wilbur J. Kilby Papers, 1849-1907
  The Wilbur J. Kilby papers are arranged alphabetically by folder title in one box, three volumes, and one oversize folder (see oversize folder 7). This series consists of appointments, circulars, correspondence, endorsements, estate accounts, graduation certificates, marriage licenses, notes from the University of Virginia law program, and receipts. Of note are the papers relating to Kilby's career as a lawyer and judge in Nansemond County, Virginia. Kilby served as county court judge, superintendent of the cemetery, commissioner of accounts of the court, and judge of the first judicial circuit. Included are appointment and election results, 1883-1905, containing official documents certifying to the authenticity of the election results; circulars endorsing Kilby for judgeship in Nansemond County, 1885-1893; graduation degrees from Randolph Macon College and the University of Virginia, 1868-1872; and his attorney license, 1872.
  Kilby was the administrator and/or executor for the estates of many family members and the collection includes accounts, receipts, promissory notes, bills, circulars for land sale, and correspondence relating to the estate accounts. On some estates Wilbur took over as executor when his father (John R. Kilby) died in 1878. Included are records for the estates of Alfred Adkins (d. 1879), John R. Kilby (d. 1878), Martha J. Kilby (d. 1888), Wilbur J. Kilby (d. 1907), Andrew McAlister (d. 1879), Nathaniel P. Phillips (d. 1878), and William Quillen (d. 1875). Of note is the estate of Alfred Akins, a freed black man of Nansemond County, Virginia. Included is Adkins will, 1879; receipts for taxes paid from 1849-1879; funeral expenses; circular announcing the public sale of the household items, 1879; inventory and appraisement of the household goods, 1879; and correspondence. Adkins left half of his estate to Alfred White (b. 1872), the son of Martha White of Pennsylvania and designated Wilbur Kilby as guardian of White, until he turned 21. Also included within the estate records are accounts, bills, correspondence and receipts relating to White's inheritance, 1879-1883.
  The correspondence, 1868-1907, includes letters from Edward A. Allen, W.E. Allen, William A. Anderson, J.D. Armstrong, W.H. Bailey Sr., Richard H. Baker, Thomas H. Barnes, George S. Bernard, R.E. Blackwell, F.J.L. Boettcher, J.E. Booker, H.W. Bradshaw, Thomas Branch, R.A. Brock, Merritt Briggs, Lee Britt, Alexander G. Brown, W.S. Brown, Henry L. Bush, P.D. Camp, W.N. Camp, William Camp, Bentley B. Campbell, Hill Carter, H.C. Cheatham, J.F. Crocker, W.B. Crowell, George H. Crump, John W. Daniel, C.H. Disbrow, John B. Donovan, Clara E. Drake, A.E. Eley, S.E. Everett, George B. Finch, L.F. Fort, S. Bassett French, Charles A. Graves, Sallie C. Harbaugh, Sarah C. Harbaugh, Z.T. Holland, Eppa Hunton, Margaret M. Jones, Thomas M. Jones, W.H. Jones, Anna M. Laise-Phillips, William Henry Lee, B.F. McLemore, Morton Marye, John B. Minor, D.J. Mood, Joel Munshell's Sons, John Murray, William W. Murray, L.T. Myers, Clarence F. Norment, Lizzie Smith Norment, George D. Old, A.C. Palmer, Charles Poindexter, Mills E. Powell, J.A. Proctor, J.T.B. Prud, J.W. Randolph & Co., Benjamin Riddick, Asa Rogers, Russell & Russell, John Seay, William B. Shands, Indie Smith, Leroy L. Smith, Thomas Kilby Smith, William R. Smith, William W. Smith, Charles F. Taylor, R.S. Thomas, Hattie Blanche Thompson, I.T. Tichenor, Elizabeth Baxton Tomlin, B.D. Tucker, James F. Twitty, D. Gardiner Tyler, J. Hope Tyler, Lyon G. Tyler, Thomas E. Upshaw, William H. White, John B. Whitehead, William Riddick Whitehead, A.C. Withers, F.C. Woodward, P. Wilson, E.A. Wright, I. Yearsley Jr., George F. Young, and N.P. Young.
  Of note are numerous letters from Lyon Gardiner Tyler (1853-1921), son of John Tyler (1790-1862), to Kilby. The two men were college roommates at the University of Virginia and many of the letters are of a friendly, personal nature, inquiring into family and planning visits. Some of the letters are requests for support and recommendations, including a letter dated 19 November 1885, asking Kilby to spread a good word for his brother, David Gardiner Tyler, who was an applicant for circuit judge in the eighth district in Virginia; letter dated 19 November 1887, asking Kilby for support of a friend running for the chancery judgeship of Richmond; and letter dated 25 July 1888, asking for Kilby's support in his bid for the presidency of William and Mary College. Tyler served as the president of William and Mary from 1888-1919.
  Also included is correspondence from David Gardiner Tyler (1846-1927), brother of Lyon Gardiner Tyler, while he served in the U.S. House of Representatives, 1893-1897, and correspondence, 1897 March 24 and 17 April 1897, from James Hoge Tyler (1846-1925), asking for Kilby's support in running for governor of Virginia. Tyler served from 1898-1902 as governor of Virginia.
  Other topics include family, legal advice, elections, deaths in the family, genealogical research, finances and stock prices, the settlement of his father's (John R. Kilby) estate, local politics in Nansemond County, commencement of the Suffolk Female Institute of 1890, and letters of recommendation. Also included are letters from Martha White, 1888, in regards to her son Alfred White; letters, 1868 April, from Edward A. Allen asking advice on how to start a preparatory school to the University of Virginia in Nansemond County, Virginia; letter, 30 April 1888, from the Commonwealth of Virginia, Auditor of Public Accounts, in response to a request by Kilby to obtain a Confederate pension for the widow of Daniel H. Christie; letter, 28 August 1893, from William Henry Lee, regarding portraits done by the artist John Sharpless; letter, 8 December 1885, from John B. Minor, professor at the University of Virginia, which was used in a circular on Kilby's bid for county judge; and a letter, 23 February 1901, from John Seay at the Virginia State Prison, regarding his trial, claiming that he was not properly represented, and asking Kilby to commute his sentence.
  - Appointments and election results, 1883-1905 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Circular for land sales, 1901-1905 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1868-1879 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1880-1889 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1895 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1896-1899 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1907 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Endorsements for judge, 1885-1893 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Estate of Alfred Adkins (d. 1879), 1849-1883 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Estate of John R. Kilby (d. 1879), 1882 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Estate of Martha J. Kilby (d. 1888), 1879-188 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Estate of Wilbur J. Kilby (d. 1907), 1907-1908 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Estate of Andrew McAlister (d. 1879), 1879-1889 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Estate of Nathaniel P. Phillips (d. 1878), 1878-1879 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Estate of William Quillen (d. 1875), 1875-1876 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Graduation certificates and attorney license, 1868-1873 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Marriage licenses, 1876-1889 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Nansemond County, Va., Circuit court, 1904-1907 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Receipts, 1874-1896 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Notebook from University of Virginia, c. 1870 (Volume on shelf)
  - Notebook on international, governmental, constitutional, and mercantile law, University of Virginia, 1870-1872 (Volume on shelf)
  - Notebook from University of Virginia, 1872 (Volume on shelf)
- Series IV: Arthur Smith Papers, 1804-1937
  The Arthur Smith papers are arranged alphabetically by folder title in one box and one oversize folder (see oversize folder 8). This series consists of account books, circulars, clippings, correspondence, daybooks, promissory notes, and receipts of Arthur Smith of Nansemond County, Virginia. Included are numerous accounts of the post office of Nansemond County, 1804-1812, where Smith was postmaster from 1804-1844. Also included are receipts for monies paid on behalf of the post office, circulars announcing rate increases, and quarterly reports. Also included is an account book of the post office, 1832-1844, contains postal accounts and a list of subscribers of various newspapers and magazines, such as the Richmond Christian Advocate, Christian Sentinel, Norfolk Herald, Norfolk Beacon, and the Philadelphia Courier (Pa.).
  Also includes a summons for Smith to appear before the justice of the peace in Suffolk, Virginia, 1849, tax receipts for Nansemond County, 1849, and receipts for the purchase of insurance from the Mutual Assurance Society of Virginia. Smith also operated a general store in Nansemond County and the collection includes a daybook, 1809-1825. The daybook records purchase amounts and payment for cloth, dry goods, hardware, tobacco, lumber, and iron.
  When Arthur Smith died in 1849, his son-in-law, John R. Kilby, was appointed executor of the estate, and receipts and promissory notes are included from the estate settlement, 1850-1853. Also included are two newspaper articles from the Norfolk Virginian Pilot on the history of Nansemond County postmasters, 1932 and 1937.
  - Account book, 1809-1830 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Account book, 1832-1844 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Daybook, 1809-1825 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Papers, 1804-1937 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Oversize materials
  - Land deed and survey between Joseph Lockhard, George Walker, and David Meade, for land in Nansemond County, Va., 1775 (Folder 1)
  - Land deed between Mills Cowper and Thomas Swepson for land in Nansemond County, Va., 1807 (Folder 1)
  - Land warrant for land in Nansemond County, Va., 1835 (Folder 1)
  - Land warrant for land in Nansemond County, Va., to David Jordan and Cadwallander W. Hawes, 1845 (Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous surveys of Nansemond County, Va., including surveys of Kilby and Riddick family lands, 1700-1902 (Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous surveys of Nansemond and Norfolk Counties, Va., and Florida, 1799-1818 (Folder 3)
  - Muster rolls and returns for the 16th Virginia Infantry, C.S.A., 1862-1864 (Folder 4)
  - Muster rolls for the 59th Virginia Militia, Commanded by Josiah Riddick, Jr., 1813 (Folder 5)
  - John R. Kilby certificates from Suffolk College, 1892-1895 (Folder 6)
  - Wilbur J. Kilby certificates from Randolph Macon College and Univeristy of Virginia, and attorney license, 1870-1885 (Folder 7)
  - Accounts of the post office of Suffolk, Va., 1804-1849 (Folder 8)